I love a great mystery,
أنا أحب الألغاز العظيمة
and I'm fascinated by the greatest unsolved mystery in science,
و مفتون بأعظم الألغاز العلمية غير المحلولة
perhaps because it's personal.
ويمكن بسبب كونها شخصية
It's about who we are,
إنه حول من نحن
and I can't help but be curious.
ولا استطيع المساعدة سوى أن أكون فضوليا
The mystery is this:
إن اللغز هو :
What is the relationship between your brain
ما هي العلاقة بين مخك
and your conscious experiences,
و تجاربك الواعية
such as your experience of the taste of chocolate
مثل تجربتك حول طعم الشوكولاتا
or the feeling of velvet?
أو إحساسك بالمخمل ؟
Now, this mystery is not new.
هذا اللغز ليس جديدا
In 1868, Thomas Huxley wrote,
في 1868 كتب توماس هكسلي
"How it is that anything so remarkable as a state of consciousness comes about
كيف يكون كل شئ ملحوظا مع حالة الوعي يأتي
as the result of irritating nervous tissue
كنتيجة لحركة مثيرة لنسيج عصبي
is just as unaccountable
لا يمكن توقعها
as the appearance of the genie when Aladdin rubbed his lamp."
كظهور الجني عندما يمسح علاء الدين المصباح
Now, Huxley knew that brain activity
لقد عرف هكسلي إن نشاط المخ
and conscious experiences are correlated,
والتجارب الواعية مترابطة معا
but he didn't know why.
لكنه لم يعرف لماذا
To the science of his day, it was a mystery.
وبالنسبة لعلوم عصره كان ذلك لغزا.
In the years since Huxley,
وفي السنوات التالية بعد هكسلي
science has learned a lot about brain activity,
تعرف العلم الكثير عن نشاط المخ
but the relationship between brain activity
ولكن العلاقة بين نشاط المخ
and conscious experiences is still a mystery.
والتجربة الحسية لا تزال لغزا
Why? Why have we made so little progress?
لماذا؟ لماذا لم نحز إلا القليل من التقدم؟
Well, some experts think that we can't solve this problem
بعض الخبراء يرون عدم إمكاننا حل المشكلة
because we lack the necessary concepts and intelligence.
لأننا تفتقد المفاهيم والذكاء، فنحن
We don't expect monkeys to solve problems in quantum mechanics,
لا نتوقع من قردة حل مشاكل الميكانيكا الكمية
and as it happens, we can't expect our species to solve this problem either.
و بهذا لا نتوقع قيام جنسنا بحل هذه المشكلة
Well, I disagree. I'm more optimistic.
حسنا، أنا أختلف. انا أكثر تفاؤلا
I think we've simply made a false assumption.
أعتقد ببساطة إننا قمنا بفرضية خاطئة
Once we fix it, we just might solve this problem.
وما أن نصلحها فقد نتمكن من حل المشكلة
Today, I'd like tell you what that assumption is,
اليوم سأخبركم ما هي هذه الفرضية
why it's false, and how to fix it.
ولماذا هي خطأ وكيف نصلحها
Let's begin with a question:
لنبدأ بسؤال
Do we see reality as it is?
هل نرى الواقع كما هو ؟
I open my eyes
أنا افتح عيني
and I have an experience that I describe as a red tomato a meter away.
وأختبر ما أصفه بطماطم حمراء على بعد متر
As a result, I come to believe that in reality,
وكنتيجة سأعتقد بأن هذا هو الواقع
there's a red tomato a meter away.
بأن هناك طماطم حمراء على بعد متر واحد
I then close my eyes, and my experience changes to a gray field,
ثم أغلق عيني وتتحول رؤيتي إلى حقل رمادي
but is it still the case that in reality, there's a red tomato a meter away?
ولكن هل ستبقى الحقيقة أن هناك طماطم حمراء
I think so, but could I be wrong?
على بعد متر؟ أعتقد ذلك ولكن هل أكون مخطئا؟
Could I be misinterpreting the nature of my perceptions?
هل يمكن أن أكون مخطئا في ترجمة ما أحس؟
We have misinterpreted our perceptions before.
لقد أخطأنا بترجمة إحساسنا سابقا
We used to think the Earth is flat, because it looks that way.
فكرنا أن الأرض مسطحة لأننا أحسسنا بها كذلك
Pythagorus discovered that we were wrong.
وأكتشف فيثاغورس بأننا كنا على خطأ
Then we thought that the Earth is the unmoving center of the Universe,
قم فكرنا بأن الأرض هي المركز الثابت للكون
again because it looks that way.
أيضا لأنها تبدو لنا كذلك
Copernicus and Galileo discovered, again, that we were wrong.
وأكتشف كوبرنيكوس و غاليليو بأننا على خطأ
Galileo then wondered if we might be misinterpreting our experiences
وفكر غاليليو بأننا قد نترجم أحاسيسنا خطأ
in other ways.
بأشكال أخرى. وكتب يقول
He wrote: "I think that tastes, odors, colors, and so on
أعتقد بأن الذوق و الروائح والألوان .. الخ
reside in consciousness.
مستقرة في وعينا
Hence if the living creature were removed, all these qualities would be annihilated."
لذا لو زال المخلوق الحي تزول كل هذه الصفات
Now, that's a stunning claim.
ولكن هذا إدعاء مذهل
Could Galileo be right?
هل يمكن أن يكون غاليليو صحيحا؟
Could we really be misinterpreting our experiences that badly?
هل يمكن أن نخطأ بتفسير إحساسنا لهذا الحد؟
What does modern science have to say about this?
ماذا يقول العلم الحديث عن هذا ؟
Well, neuroscientists tell us that about a third of the brain's cortex
علماء الأعصاب يقولون إن ثلث قشرة المخ
is engaged in vision.
مخصصة للبصر
When you simply open your eyes and look about this room,
عندما تفتح عينيك و تنظر حول الغرفة ستعمل
billions of neurons and trillions of synapses are engaged.
بلايين الخلايا العصبية وترليونات العقد تتشارك.
Now, this is a bit surprising,
وهذا مثير للدهشة فعلا
because to the extent that we think about vision at all,
لأن فكرتنا عن البصر عامة
we think of it as like a camera.
هو إنه مثل الكاميرا
It just takes a picture of objective reality as it is.
يأخذ صورة الشئ من الواقع كما هو
Now, there is a part of vision that's like a camera:
نعم هناك جزء من البصر مثل الكاميرا
the eye has a lens that focuses an image on the back of the eye
فلدى العين عدسة تركز الصورة في خلفية العين
where there are 130 million photoreceptors,
حيث توجد 130 مليون خلية بصرية مستلمة
so the eye is like a 130-megapixel camera.
فالعين هي مثل كاميرا ذات 130 مليون بكسل
But that doesn't explain the billions of neurons
لكن هذا لا يفسر البلايين من العقد العصبية
and trillions of synapses that are engaged in vision.
و ترليونات الشبكات المرتبطة بالبصر
What are these neurons up to?
ماذا تفعل هذه العقد العصبية ؟
Well, neuroscientists tell us that they are creating, in real time,
يقول علماء الأعصاب بأنها تخلق بشكل آني
all the shapes, objects, colors, and motions that we see.
جميع الأشكال والألوان والحركات التي نراها
It feels like we're just taking a snapshot of this room the way it is,
ويبدو إننا سنأخذ صورة لهذه الغرفة كما هي
but in fact, we're constructing everything that we see.
لكن في الواقع بأننا ننشئ كل ما نراه
We don't construct the whole world at once.
نحن لا ننشئ كل العالم مرة واحدة
We construct what we need in the moment.
نحن ننشئ ما نحتاج في تلك اللحظة
Now, there are many demonstrations that are quite compelling
ولكن هناك بعض الأشياء التي تفرض نفسها
that we construct what we see.
بأننا ننشئ ما نراه
I'll just show you two.
سأريكم فقط إثنين من ذلك وفي المثال التالي
In this example, you see some red discs with bits cut out of them,
ترون أقراص دائرية بأجزاء مقطوعة منها
but if I just rotate the disks a little bit,
لكني لو أدرت هذه الأقراص قليلا
suddenly, you see a 3D cube pop out of the screen.
فجأة ترى مكعبا مجسما يخرج من الشاشة
Now, the screen of course is flat,
ولكن الشاشة مسطحة بالتأكيد
so the three-dimensional cube that you're experiencing
لذلك فإن المكعب المجسم الذي تراه
must be your construction.
هو بناؤك الخاص
In this next example,
وفي المثال التالي فإنك ترى
you see glowing blue bars with pretty sharp edges
خطوطا زرقاء مشعة بحواف حادة
moving across a field of dots.
تتحرك عبر حقل من النقاط
In fact, no dots move.
في الواقع النقاط لا تتحرك
All I'm doing from frame to frame is changing the colors of dots
كل ما أفعله هو تغيير لون النقاط
from blue to black or black to blue.
من الأزرق إلى السود ومن الأسود إلى الزرق
But when I do this quickly,
ولكن عندما اقوم بذلك بسرعة
your visual system creates the glowing blue bars
فإن نظام البصر يخلق وهجا أزرق في الخطوط
with the sharp edges and the motion.
بالحافات الحادة والحركة
There are many more examples, but these are just two
وهناك الكثير من الأمثلة وهذان إثنين منها
that you construct what you see.
بأنك تنشئ ما ترى
But neuroscientists go further.
ولكن علماء الأعصاب يذهبون ابعد من ذلك
They say that we reconstruct reality.
فيقولون نحن نعيد بناء الواقع
So, when I have an experience that I describe as a red tomato,
إذا عندما يكون إدراكي ما أصفه بطماطم حمراء
that experience is actually an accurate reconstruction
فإن هذا الإدراك هو إعادة تركيب دقيقة
of the properties of a real red tomato
لخواص طماطم حمراء حقيقية
that would exist even if I weren't looking.
تكون موجودة حتى لو لم أكن أراها
Now, why would neuroscientists say that we don't just construct,
الآن لماذا يقول علماء الأعصاب أننا لا ننشئ
we reconstruct?
بل نعيد الإنشاء ؟
Well, the standard argument given
الحجة العامة المتوفرة
is usually an evolutionary one.
إعتياديا هي من فكر التطور
Those of our ancestors who saw more accurately
كان لأجدادنا الذين ابصروا بشكل أكثر دقة
had a competitive advantage compared to those who saw less accurately,
ميزة متفوقة على الذين يبصرون بدقة أقل
and therefore they were more likely to pass on their genes.
لذلك كان من المحتمل أن يمرروا جيناتهم لنا
We are the offspring of those who saw more accurately,
وكنا طفرة من الذين ابصروا بدقة أعلى
and so we can be confident that, in the normal case,
يمكن أن نكون واثقين بأنه في الحالات العامة
our perceptions are accurate.
بأن إحساسنا دقيق
You see this in the standard textbooks.
وتجد هذا في الكتب المدرسية العامة
One textbook says, for example,
يرد في أحد الكتب مثلا
"Evolutionarily speaking,
"للحديث عن التطور
vision is useful precisely because it is so accurate."
فإن البصر مفيد بدقة لأنه دقيق جدا"
So the idea is that accurate perceptions are fitter perceptions.
عليه فإن فكرة أن الإدراك الدقيق هو
They give you a survival advantage.
الإدراك الأصح وهذا يعطينا الأمان المريح
Now, is this correct?
ولكن هل هذا صحيح ؟
Is this the right interpretation of evolutionary theory?
هل هذا هو التفسير الصحيح لنظرية التطور؟
Well, let's first look at a couple of examples in nature.
حسنا، لنلق نظرة على مثالين من الطبيعة
The Australian jewel beetle
الخنفساء اللماعة الاسترالية
is dimpled, glossy and brown.
اللماعة المبططة البنية
The female is flightless.
الأنثى لا تطير
The male flies, looking, of course, for a hot female.
الذكر يطير باحثا طبعا عن أنثى جاهزة
When he finds one, he alights and mates.
وعندما يجد واحدة يهبط و يتزاوجان
There's another species in the outback,
ولكن في الخلفية يقف نوع آخر
Homo sapiens.
حكماء البشر
The male of this species has a massive brain
فإن الذكرمن هذا النوع له مخ أكبر
that he uses to hunt for cold beer.
يستخدمه للبحث عن قنينة بيرة باردة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when he finds one, he drains it,
وعندما يجد واحدة يشربها حتى الثمالة
and sometimes throws the bottle into the outback.
وأحيانا يرمي القنينة خلف الدار
Now, as it happens, these bottles are dimpled, glossy,
ولكن هذه القناني لماعة و مبططة
and just the right shade of brown to tickle the fancy of these beetles.
ولونها بني يحرك عواطف هذا النوع من الخنافس
The males swarm all over the bottles trying to mate.
فتهجم جموع الذكورعلى القناني تحاول التزاوج
They lose all interest in the real females.
فاقدة الإهتمام بالأناث الحقيقية
Classic case of the male leaving the female for the bottle.
مثل حال الذكر الذي يفضل القنينة على الأنثى
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
The species almost went extinct.
وكاد هذا النوع من الخنافس ينقرض
Australia had to change its bottles to save its beetles.
وأضطرت استراليا لتغيير القناني لحفظ النوع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, the males had successfully found females for thousands,
و نجح الذكور في إيجاد الإناث لآلاف
perhaps millions of years.
أو ربما لملايين السنين
It looked like they saw reality as it is, but apparently not.
ويبدو إنهم رأوا الحقيقة كما هي ولكن كلا
Evolution had given them a hack.
التطور أعطاهم المعرفة
A female is anything dimpled, glossy and brown,
بأن الأنثى مبططة و لماعة و بنية اللون
the bigger the better.
وكلما كانت أكبر كانت افضل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Even when crawling all over the bottle, the male couldn't discover his mistake.
وعندما كان يزحف على الزجاجة لم يكتشف الفرق
Now, you might say, beetles, sure, they're very simple creatures,
و قد يقال إن الخنافس فعلا مخلوقات بسيطة
but surely not mammals.
ولكنها بالتأكيد ليست ثديية
Mammals don't rely on tricks.
والثدييات لا تعتمد على حيل
Well, I won't dwell on this, but you get the idea. (Laughter)
حسنا لن أناقش هذا ولكن فهمتم الفكرة (ضحك)
So this raises an important technical question:
ويثير هذا سؤالا تقنيا مهما .. هل يفضل
Does natural selection really favor seeing reality as it is?
الأنتقاء الطبيعي رؤية الواقع كما هو ؟
Fortunately, we don't have to wave our hands and guess;
لحسن الحظ ليس علينا أن نضرب ايدينا و نحزر
evolution is a mathematically precise theory.
فالتطور هو نظرية رياضية دقيقة جدا
We can use the equations of evolution to check this out.
يمكننا إستخدام معادلات التطور لأختبار هذا
We can have various organisms in artificial worlds compete
يمكن جعل مختلف الأحياء تتنافس في جو صناعي
and see which survive and which thrive,
لنعرف أيها سينجو وأيها ينقرض
which sensory systems are more fit.
أي نظام حسي أكثر لياقة
A key notion in those equations is fitness.
الفكرة الأساس في هذه المعادلات هي اللياقة
Consider this steak:
تصور هذه الشريحة من اللحم
What does this steak do for the fitness of an animal?
ماذا ستفعل هذه الشريحة للياقة حيوان ما؟
Well, for a hungry lion looking to eat, it enhances fitness.
فهي لأسد جائع يبحث عن طعام تدعم لياقته
For a well-fed lion looking to mate, it doesn't enhance fitness.
ولأسد شبعان يريد التزاوج لن تزيد لياقته
And for a rabbit in any state, it doesn't enhance fitness,
ولأرنب في أي حال كان لن تزيد لياقته
so fitness does depend on reality as it is, yes,
إذا تعتمد اللياقة على الواقع كما هو
but also on the organism, its state and its action.
ولكنها تعتمد ايضا على حالة و حركة الحيوان
Fitness is not the same thing as reality as it is,
فاللياقة ليست نفسها كما هو الواقع نفسه
and it's fitness, and not reality as it is,
واللياقة ليست في الواقع نفسها
that figures centrally in the equations of evolution.
التي تتحدد في معادلات التطور.
So, in my lab,
لذلك، وفي مختبري
we have run hundreds of thousands of evolutionary game simulations
أجرينا مئات الألوف من محاكاة ألعاب التطور
with lots of different randomly chosen worlds
بإستخدام العديد من عوالم مختارة عشوائيا
and organisms that compete for resources in those worlds.
ومخلوقات تتنافس على موارد هذه العوالم
Some of the organisms see all of the reality,
بعض المخلوقات ترى كل الواقع
others see just part of the reality,
وبعضها ترى جزءا من الواقع
and some see none of the reality,
وبعضها لا ترى الواقع نهائيا
only fitness.
اللياقة فقط
Who wins?
فمن يفوز ؟ لا أحب أن أخبركم
In almost every simulation,
وفي أغلب عمليات المحاكاة
organisms that see none of reality
فإن المخلوقات التي لا ترى الواقع نهائيا
but are just tuned to fitness
ولكنها مهيئة فقط لتتوافق مع اللياقة، تدفع
drive to extinction all the organisms that perceive reality as it is.
لإنقراض المخلوقات التي ترى الواقع كما هو
So the bottom line is, evolution does not favor veridical,
الخلاصة هي أن التطور لا يحابي الحقيقة،
or accurate perceptions.
أو الإدراك الدقيق
Those perceptions of reality go extinct.
إن إدراك الواقع بدأ بالأنقراض
Now, this is a bit stunning.
والآن سنرى شيئا مذهلا
How can it be that not seeing the world accurately
كيف يمكن عندما لا نرى العالم بدقة
gives us a survival advantage?
أن تكون لنا أفضلية في البقاء؟
That is a bit counterintuitive.
إن هذا ضد المعقول
But remember the jewel beetle.
ولكن تذكر الخنفساء اللماعة
The jewel beetle survived for thousands, perhaps millions of years,
التي نجت لألاف و ربما ملايين السنين
using simple tricks and hacks.
بإستخدام حيل ومعارف بسيطة
What the equations of evolution are telling us
ما تخبرنا معادلات التطور هو أن الحيوانات
is that all organisms, including us, are in the same boat as the jewel beetle.
ومنها نحن في نفس المركب مع الخنفساء
We do not see reality as it is.
نحن لا نرى الواقع كما هو.
We're shaped with tricks and hacks that keep us alive.
نحن صاغتنا حيل ومعارف أبقتنا أحياء
Still,
ولكن،
we need some help with our intuitions.
نحن نحتاج إلى بعض المساعدة في حدسنا
How can not perceiving reality as it is be useful?
كيف يمكن لعدم إدراك الواقع أن يكون مفيدا؟
Well, fortunately, we have a very helpful metaphor:
لكن لحسن الحظ لدينا تشبيها مساعدا
the desktop interface on your computer.
التفاعل مع سطح المكتب في حاسوبك
Consider that blue icon for a TED Talk that you're writing.
خذ الرمز الأزرق لمحادثة TED التي تكتبها
Now, the icon is blue and rectangular
هذا الرمز أزرق ومستطيل الشكل
and in the lower right corner of the desktop.
وفي الزاوية اليمنى الدنيا من سطح المكتب
Does that mean that the text file itself in the computer is blue,
هل يعني هذا أن الحروف زرقاء ومستطيلة
rectangular, and in the lower right-hand corner of the computer?
وفي الزاوية اليمنى الدنيا في الحاسوب؟
Of course not.
بالطبع كلا.
Anyone who thought that misinterprets the purpose of the interface.
هل فكر أحد بأن ذلك تفسير خاطئ لسبب التفاعل
It's not there to show you the reality of the computer.
إنه ليس هناك ليريك واقع الحاسوب
In fact, it's there to hide that reality.
في الحقيقة إنه هناك ليخفي ذلك الواقع
You don't want to know about the diodes
قد لا تريد معرفة أي شيء عن الصمامات
and resistors and all the megabytes of software.
والمقاومات و الميغابايتات من البرمجيات
If you had to deal with that, you could never write your text file
إذا كنت ستهتم بكل ذاك فلن تكتب اي نص
or edit your photo.
أو تقوم بتحرير صورك
So the idea is that evolution has given us an interface
فالفكرة هي أن التطور أعطانا واجهة
that hides reality and guides adaptive behavior.
تخفي الواقع و تقود تصرفنا المتكيف
Space and time, as you perceive them right now,
الفضاء والواقع كما تدركهما الآن
are your desktop.
هي سطح المكتب أو الشاشة
Physical objects are simply icons in that desktop.
الأشياء الطبيعية هي فقط ايقونات على الشاشة
There's an obvious objection.
وهناك إعتراض واضح
Hoffman, if you think that train coming down the track at 200 MPH
إذا فكرت إن القطار القادم على السكة بسرعة
is just an icon of your desktop,
بسرعة 200 كم/ساعة هوفقط أيقونة على شاشة
why don't you step in front of it?
لماذا لا تقف في طريقه؟
And after you're gone, and your theory with you,
وبعد أن تبتعد انت ونظرياتك
we'll know that there's more to that train than just an icon.
سنعرف إن هناك ما هو أكثر من ايقونة قطار
Well, I wouldn't step in front of that train
نعم أنا لن اقف أمام ذلك القطار
for the same reason
لنفس السبب الذي يمنعني
that I wouldn't carelessly drag that icon to the trash can:
من سحب الأيقونة بلا مبالاة إلى سلة المهملات
not because I take the icon literally --
ليس لأنني اتعامل مع الأيقونة حرفيا لأن هذه
the file is not literally blue or rectangular --
الملفات ليست حرفيا زرقاء أو مستطيلة
but I do take it seriously.
ولكني آخذ الموضوع بشكل جدي
I could lose weeks of work.
لأنني سأفقد أسابيع من العمل
Similarly, evolution has shaped us
وبشكل مماثل فإن التطور قد شكلنا
with perceptual symbols that are designed to keep us alive.
برموز حسية صممت لتحفظنا احياء
We'd better take them seriously.
لذلك علينا ان نأخذها بجدية
If you see a snake, don't pick it up.
إذا رايت افعى فلا تلتقطها
If you see a cliff, don't jump off.
إذا رايت جرفا صخريا فلا تقفز منه
They're designed to keep us safe, and we should take them seriously.
إنها مصممة لضمان سلامتنا ويجب أخذها بجدية
That does not mean that we should take them literally.
ولكن هذا لا يعني اخذها حرفيا
That's a logical error.
لأن هذا خطأ منطقي
Another objection: There's nothing really new here.
إعتراض آخر: لا يوجد فعلا شيء جديد هنا
Physicists have told us for a long time that the metal of that train looks solid
يقول العلماء بأن معدن القطار يبدو صلدا
but really it's mostly empty space with microscopic particles zipping around.
بينما هو فضاء خالي تدور فيه أجسام مجهرية
There's nothing new here.
لا شيء جديد هنا
Well, not exactly.
ولكن ليس بالضبط
It's like saying, I know that that blue icon on the desktop
إنها مثل قول اعرف إن الأيقونة الزرقاء
is not the reality of the computer,
على الشاشة هي ليست الحاسوب في الواقع
but if I pull out my trusty magnifying glass and look really closely,
ولكن لو أخذت عدسة مكبرة وأنظر عن قرب فعلا
I see little pixels,
سأرى البكسلات الصغيرة
and that's the reality of the computer.
وهذه هي حقيقة الحاسوب. حسنا ، ليس فعلا
Well, not really -- you're still on the desktop, and that's the point.
فلا نزال على الشاشة، وتلك هي الفكرة
Those microscopic particles are still in space and time:
فالجزيئات المجهرية لا تزال في الفضاء والوقت
they're still in the user interface.
وهي لا تزال في واجهة المستخدم
So I'm saying something far more radical than those physicists.
لذا سأقول شيئا أكثر تطرفا من هؤلاء العلماء
Finally, you might object,
وأخيرا قد تعترضون
look, we all see the train,
أنظروا نحن جميعا نرى القطار
therefore none of us constructs the train.
أي لا أحد منا سينشئ القطار
But remember this example.
ولكن تذكروا هذا المثال
In this example, we all see a cube,
في هذا المثال سنرى جمينا مكعبا
but the screen is flat,
ولكن الشاشة مسطحة
so the cube that you see is the cube that you construct.
إذا المكعب الذي تراه هو المكعب الذي تنشؤه
We all see a cube
نحن جميعا نرى مكعبا
because we all, each one of us, constructs the cube that we see.
لأننا وكل واحد فينا ينشئ المكعب الذي يراه
The same is true of the train.
والحقيقة نفسها عن القطار
We all see a train because we each see the train that we construct,
نحن نرى القطار لأن كل منا رأى قطارا انشأه
and the same is true of all physical objects.
وهذا صح لكل الأشياء الطبيعية.
We're inclined to think that perception is like a window on reality as it is.
ونحن ميالون لفكرة أن الإدراك مثل شباك نرى الواقع عبره
The theory of evolution is telling us that this is an incorrect interpretation
ولكن نظرية التطور تقول بأن هذا تفسير خاطئ
of our perceptions.
لتصوراتنا.
Instead, reality is more like a 3D desktop
بدلا من ذلك فإن الواقع مثل شاشة مجسمة
that's designed to hide the complexity of the real world
مصممة لتخفي تعقيد العالم الحقيقي
and guide adaptive behavior.
وتقود السلوك القابل للتكيف
Space as you perceive it is your desktop.
الفضاء الذي تدركه هو سطح المكتب
Physical objects are just the icons in that desktop.
والأشياء الطبيعية هي ايقونات على الشاشة
We used to think that the Earth is flat because it looks that way.
تعودنا على إن الأرض مسطحة لأنها تبدو كذلك
Then we thought that the Earth is the unmoving center of reality
ثم اعتقدنا إن الأرض مركز الكون الثابت
We were wrong.
وكنا مخطئين
We had misinterpreted our perceptions.
لقد فسرنا احساسنا بطريقة خاطئة
Now we believe that spacetime and objects
والآن نعتقد بأن الفضاء والوقت والأشياء
are the nature of reality as it is.
هي طبيعة الواقع كما هو
The theory of evolution is telling us that once again, we're wrong.
ونظرية التطور تقول بأننا مخطئون مجددا
We're misinterpreting the content of our perceptual experiences.
إننا نخطئ في تفسير ما يتلقاه إحساسنا
There's something that exists when you don't look,
هناك شيء موجود عندما لا تنظر
but it's not spacetime and physical objects.
لكنه ليس الفضاء والوقت والأشياء الطبيعية
It's as hard for us to let go of spacetime and objects
من الصعب ترك فكرة الوقت الفضاء والاشياء
as it is for the jewel beetle to let go of its bottle.
كما كان من الصعب على الخنفساء ترك القنينة
Why? Because we're blind to our own blindnesses.
لماذا؟ لأننا عميان عن معرفة عمانا الخاص
But we have an advantage over the jewel beetle:
ولكننا افضل من الخنفساء اللماعة
our science and technology.
بعلومنا و تقنياتنا
By peering through the lens of a telescope
بالنظر عبر عدسة التلسكوب
we discovered that the Earth is not the unmoving center of reality,
اكتشفنا بأن الأرض ليست مركز الكون الثابت
and by peering through the lens of the theory of evolution
ومن خلال النظر في عدسة نظرية التطور
we discovered that spacetime and objects
إكتشفنا بأن الفضاء الوقت والاشياء
are not the nature of reality.
ليست طبيعة الحقيقة
When I have a perceptual experience that I describe as a red tomato,
عندما أدرك بأنني اصف طماطم حمراء
I am interacting with reality,
فأنا اتفاعل مع الحقيقة
but that reality is not a red tomato and is nothing like a red tomato.
ولكن الواقع ليس طماطم حمراء ولا يشبهها
Similarly, when I have an experience that I describe as a lion or a steak,
كذلك عندما اصف تجربتي لأسد أو شريحة لحم
I'm interacting with reality,
فأنا اتفاعل مع الواقع
but that reality is not a lion or a steak.
ولكن هذا ليس فعلا اسدا او شريحة لحم
And here's the kicker:
وهنا يأتي الإعتراض
When I have a perceptual experience that I describe as a brain, or neurons,
عندما أدرك حسيا وأنا أصف المخ أو عقده
I am interacting with reality,
فإنني أتفاعل مع الحقيقة
but that reality is not a brain or neurons
ولكن ذلك الواقع ليس المخ أو العقد العصبية
and is nothing like a brain or neurons.
ولا يشبه المخ أو العقد العصبية
is the real source of cause and effect
فهو المصدر الحقيقي للعلة والتأثير
in the world -- not brains, not neurons.
في العالم وليس المخ وليس العقد العصبية
Brains and neurons have no causal powers.
فإن المخ وعقده ليست لها قدرات عرضية
They cause none of our perceptual experiences,
لأنها لا تسبب أيا من تجاربنا الحسية
and none of our behavior.
ولا أي من تصرفاتنا لأن المخ
Brains and neurons are a species-specific set of symbols, a hack.
والعقد العصبية خاصة برموز نوع معين، مخرج.
What does this mean for the mystery of consciousness?
ماذا يعني هذا بالنسبة لسر الوعي ؟
Well, it opens up new possibilities.
حسنا إنها تفتح إمكانيات جديدة
For instance,
مثلا ، يجوز أن يكون
perhaps reality is some vast machine that causes our conscious experiences.
الواقع ماكنة كبيرة تتسبب في خبرتنا الواعية
I doubt this, but it's worth exploring.
أشك بذلك ولكنها تستحق الإستكشاف أو يمكن أن
Perhaps reality is some vast, interacting network of conscious agents,
الواقع نظاما تفاعليا هائلا من عوامل الوعي
simple and complex, that cause each other's conscious experiences.
بسيطا أو معقدا شبكة تفاعلية من تجارب واعية
Actually, this isn't as crazy an idea as it seems,
وبالفعل فليست هذه فكرة مجنونة كما تبدو
and I'm currently exploring it.
وأنا الآن أبحث فيها
But here's the point:
ولكن النقطة هي
Once we let go of our massively intuitive
وما أن نترك حدسنا الكبير
but massively false assumption about the nature of reality,
وفرضيتنا الخاطئة الكبيرة حول طبيعة الواقع
it opens up new ways to think about life's greatest mystery.
تنفتح أمامنا طرق جديدة لنفكر في أعظم لغز
I bet that reality will end up turning out to be more fascinating
و أراهن بأن الواقع سوف يكون أكثر فتنة
and unexpected than we've ever imagined.
وسيكون غير متوقعا ولم نتخيله
The theory of evolution presents us with the ultimate dare:
وستقدم لنا نظرية التطور التحدي الأكبر و هو
Dare to recognize that perception is not about seeing truth,
التمييز بأن الإدراك ليس حول رؤية الحقيقة
it's about having kids.
ولكن حول حصولنا على الأولاد
And by the way, even this TED is just in your head.
وبالمناسبة فحتى علامة TED هذه هي في راسكم فقط
Thank you very much.
شكرا كثيرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: If that's really you there, thank you.
كريس أندرسون: إذا كنت انت حقيقة هناك.. فشكرا لك
So there's so much from this.
واذن فلدينا الكثير لنأخذه من هذا.
I mean, first of all, some people may just be profoundly depressed
ما أقصد هو إن البعض سيكون مكتئبا كثيرا
at the thought that, if evolution does not favor reality,
حول فكرة إن التطور لا يحابي الواقع
I mean, doesn't that to some extent undermine all our endeavors here,
أعني ألا يعني ذلك تلغيم جميع محاولاتنا هنا
all our ability to think that we can think the truth,
كل قدرتنا على التفكير بأننا نفكر الحقيقة
possibly even including your own theory, if you go there?
وممكن حتى نظرياتكم الخاصة إن فهمتم هذا؟
Donald Hoffman: Well, this does not stop us from a successful science.
دونالد هوفمان: حسنا ولكن هذا لا يوقفنا عن العلوم الناجحة
What we have is one theory that turned out to be false,
كل ما لدينا هو إن إحدى نظرياتنا بانت خطأ
that perception is like reality and reality is like our perceptions.
بأن إدراكنا مثل الواقع والواقع مثل إدراكنا
That theory turns out to be false.
وأن النظرية تبين خطؤها
Okay, throw that theory away.
حسنا لنرمي تلك النظرية بعيدا
That doesn't stop us from now postulating all sorts of other theories
وهذا لا يمنعنا من قبول كل أنواع النظريات
about the nature of reality,
حول طبيعة الواقع
so it's actually progress to recognize that one of our theories was false.
إذا تطورنا فعلا لنعرف إن إحدى نظرياتنا خطأ
So science continues as normal. There's no problem here.
وتستمر العلوم بشكل طبيعي وبلا مشكلة
CA: So you think it's possible -- (Laughter) --
كريس: إذا ، هل تعتقد بأن ذلك ممكن؟ (ضحك)
This is cool, but what you're saying I think is it's possible that evolution
هذا رائع. ولكن ما تقول هو بأن التطور يمكن
can still get you to reason.
يبقى قادرا على إعطائك سببا
DH: Yes. Now that's a very, very good point.
دونالد: نعم ويبدو إن هذه نقطة جيدة جدا جدا
The evolutionary game simulations that I showed were specifically about perception,
إن محاكاة لعبة التطور هي عن الإدراك خاصة
and they do show that our perceptions have been shaped
و تبين بأن إدراكنا قد تمت صياغته
not to show us reality as it is,
لا لترينا الواقع كما هو ولكن هذا
but that does not mean the same thing about our logic or mathematics.
لا يعني نفس الشيء عن المنطق والرياضيات
We haven't done these simulations, but my bet is that we'll find
نحن لم نقم بالمحاكاة ولكن أراهن بأننا سنجد
that there are some selection pressures for our logic and our mathematics
بعض الضغوط المختارة على منطقنا و رياضياتنا
to be at least in the direction of truth.
لتكون على الاقل في إتجاه الحقيقة
I mean, if you're like me, math and logic is not easy.
أي إذا كنتم معي فالرياضة والمنطق ليست سهلة
We don't get it all right, but at least the selection pressures are not
و لا نعيها لكن على الأقل فإن ضغوط الأختيار
uniformly away from true math and logic.
ليست بعيدة عن الرياضيات الحقيقية والمنطق
So I think that we'll find that we have to look at each cognitive faculty
لذا سنجد أن علينا النظر لكل حاسة على حدة
one at a time and see what evolution does to it.
واحدة في كل مرة لمعرفة ماذا فعل لها التطور
What's true about perception may not be true about math and logic.
الصحيح عن الإدراك ليس صحيحا عن المنطق
CA: I mean, really what you're proposing is a kind of modern-day Bishop Berkeley
كريس: أي إن ما تقترحه هو مقولة بيشب بيركلي بشكل حديث
interpretation of the world:
تفسير وترجمة العالم
consciousness causes matter, not the other way around.
الإحساس يصنع المادة وليس العكس
DH: Well, it's slightly different than Berkeley.
دونالد: نعم ولكن بإختلاف قليل عن بيركلي
Berkeley thought that, he was a deist, and he thought that the ultimate
بيركلي كان متدينا وقد فكر بذلك وإعتقد إن
nature of reality is God and so forth,
مطلق الواقع في الطبيعة هو الله
and I don't need to go where Berkeley's going,
وأنا لا أحتاج الى السير في طريق بيركلي
so it's quite a bit different from Berkeley.
لذا فإنه يختلف قليلا عن بيركلي
I call this conscious realism. It's actually a very different approach.
أنا أسميها الواقعية الواعية وهي تختلف فعلا
CA: Don, I could literally talk with you for hours, and I hope to do that.
كريس: دون يمكنني التحدث معك ساعات فعلا وأأمل ذلك
Thanks so much for that. DH: Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لذلك شكرا لك (تصفيق)